[SPEAKER_00]: When a person begins to contemplate anicca, or if they realize that everything, they think everything is impermanent, what then is the best investment for that person?
[SPEAKER_00]: What should they do about it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because a lot of people say, well, everything is impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: Thus, nothing matters.
[SPEAKER_00]: I can do whatever I want, because it's all going to end, you know, this life.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's all going to end anyway, so it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the face, yeah, in the face of that anxiety of anicca...
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, if they feel anxiety, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: But a person who is saying, oh, it doesn't matter what I do then, they won't probably even be feeling that anxiety.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if you're feeling anxiety, dismissal will not free you from anxiety.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can say nothing matters, but you still feel anxiety, which is very unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, oh, what do I do?
[SPEAKER_01]: I can keep saying nothing matters, but anxiety is still there.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, what do I do?
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if a person does genuinely has sense of anicca through anxiety and recognition of that non-control and, yeah, things will end and that will affect me, well, yeah, they need to recognize it exactly as something
[SPEAKER_01]: Something that must be addressed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not like... Something that must be addressed at the root level.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not something that they can just find the answer to, and then move on with their lives.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because, well, those lives are anicca, and that's what they're understanding.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in other words, they have to take it seriously.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just try to get rid of the discomfort.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, tell me what anicca is, tell me what to do so I get rid of this comfort of anxiety, not so I fully understand what anicca is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you can temporarily get rid of this discomfort and anxiety, but as I said many times before, anxiety is a symptom of an existential issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a problem.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, unless you remove the problem, these symptoms will keep coming back up, one way or the other.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, things will be reminding you of anicca one way or the other, doesn't matter how much you try to deal with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the first thing you do then is take the Buddhist teaching seriously.
[SPEAKER_01]: Take the gradual training seriously.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't just try to get rid of the current pain that bothers you, but recognize your liability to pain as already being an issue.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if everything is fine now and there is no anxiety now, there could be anxiety now and things could not be fine now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, oh, well, that would affect me.
[SPEAKER_01]: Thus, recognition of that is already something that affects you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you realize this is the level I must practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, take the gradual training seriously then.
[SPEAKER_01]: The precepts, the guarding of the sense doors, and, yeah, reading the suttas, studying and getting the more understanding of what the Buddha was teaching.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's dealing with anxiety, dealing with recognition of impermanence.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's, well, it's a lifelong task, in a sense of, if you are very committed, you might do it quickly, but your life will then change forever, as somebody who has understood anicca and is free from suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you're not doing it quickly, if you're not so committed, it will take you probably a full lifetime to get closer to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Either way, if you recognize you have to deal with it, your life cannot remain the same.
[SPEAKER_01]: As in life of sensuality, carelessness and everything else, leading up to that point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, don't think anxiety is something, oh, I have a problem with anxiety, something's wrong with me, let me get rid of that, go back... No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a symptom of an underlying problem that shows you that maybe, you know, this life and existence is not the way you would like to think it is, or that everybody else seems to think it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if it were so, why are you anxious?
[SPEAKER_01]: If sensuality is enough to keep your mind happy, contented, peaceful, calm, why are you not always happy, contented, peaceful and calm?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, maybe that's not the answer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe the way you're engaging the world and the views you have with the world... Maybe that's why I'm anxious.
[SPEAKER_01]: Maybe my anxiety is a symptom of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That things actually are not aligned.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yeah, Anicca is exactly that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Things are unownable, not yours, yet here you are, living your life as you're the master controller of your body, your senses, your ownership, people and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: A complete blatant contradiction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anxiety, every now and then, reminds you of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, do something about it before it's too late.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is?
[SPEAKER_01]: Which is what I just described.
[SPEAKER_01]: Study the suttas, keep the precepts strictly, gradual training, and, yeah, realize that it's a something that will, one way or the other, it needs to affect your life at the very basis of your existence.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not something you can do in response to this particular state, and then I go back to my values from before.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because the one common response is trying to appreciate everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now that everything...
[SPEAKER_00]: I realize everything's anicca, everything's impermanent.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's difficult.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll just appreciate it.
[SPEAKER_00]: I'll just delight in everything.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even more.
[SPEAKER_01]: Double down.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's anicca.
[SPEAKER_01]: Double down in my acceptance.
[SPEAKER_01]: Right.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you then find out that you have a terminal cancer, maybe a week to live,
[SPEAKER_01]: Would that appreciation keep you calm and unaffected and fearless in face of death, not suffering?
[SPEAKER_01]: Would you be able to equally appreciate and accept that and enjoy, enjoy your chemo and everything else and the torture you have to go through and, you know, seeing your family sort of grieve over you and while you're still alive?
[SPEAKER_01]: Appreciate every moment.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a blessing.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it's not.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Life has its blessings, but not all of it is a blessing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's the recognition.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what Buddha said.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the life is not...
[SPEAKER_01]: If the life were only the life of misery, beings would not be enamored with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: If the life were only life of blessings and appreciation, well, beings would not be disgusted with it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, life is both, and you use wisdom to recognize.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, don't be irrationally averse to everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, there are blessings, there are things you should appreciate, but recognize that it's all within the nature of things not being in control, and the nature of things being subject to change in its core, and that is inaccessible to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't affect that, you can't prevent that.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, keeping that in mind, then, you put your appreciation in perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't use appreciation to deal with anicca.
[SPEAKER_01]: You use anicca to not get careless with your appreciation.
[SPEAKER_01]: And same, you use anicca to not get careless with your non-appreciation or aversion.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you use anicca, wisdom of recognition of the nature of things, to keep yourself in check.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, in order to do that, you need to stop trying to get rid of it through appreciation or whatever else you might be doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the only reason people would be doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: To get rid of discomfort of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, no, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: I accept this, actually.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not up to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you know, the mountains coming to crush you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yes, I accept that.
[SPEAKER_01]: What?
[SPEAKER_01]: Who are you to even accept that?
[SPEAKER_01]: You have no say.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whether you accept or not, this is the inevitable outcome.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you saying that you appreciate and accept this, it's just you trying to appease yourself in the face of something you have no control over.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: But you need to stop trying to get rid of it, recognize it as a symptom, and then, gradual training.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're trying to get control again.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're trying to repossess it, exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, no, no.
[SPEAKER_01]: I wanted that to happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, you didn't.
[SPEAKER_00]: Nobody wants that to happen.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Gradual picking up, gradual training, gradual development, gradual composing,
[SPEAKER_01]: When I say gradual, I don't mean take it easy.
[SPEAKER_01]: I just mean you do need to do it gradually.
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to start on that level of virtue, unblemished, unbroken virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, take it seriously, the behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, from there, you know, your speech will become more wholesome than even your thoughts.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you will be able to actually
[SPEAKER_01]: Withstand more of the recognition of anicca and anxiety without having too much pressure of, I must deal with this, and then jump into one view or the other, or one action or the other, because it's unbearable to you.
[SPEAKER_01]: The only reason it's unbearable, because the mind is too weak in relation to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: The mind is too weak, because you haven't been practicing sense restraining God, in the sense those taming the beasts.
[SPEAKER_01]: You haven't been doing that, so they're still very powerful.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, how can you then be in control of them, unless you can physically, at least, be able to go around them, and not let them drag you around?
[SPEAKER_01]: That composure, they will be able to face the anxiety or any other unpleasantness, will be there.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because you build a basis for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not, oh, how do I face anxiety?
[SPEAKER_01]: No.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are already facing it by not acting out of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: By not breaking your virtue when you're anxious, you are already facing anxiety.
[SPEAKER_01]: You are doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it doesn't feel like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not when you think you're doing the work or not.
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's a mountain.
[SPEAKER_01]: There you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there were suttas where everybody said, what is samādhi?
[SPEAKER_01]: Samādhi is basically a monk who practices mind... basically the mind... a monk who practices keeping his mind unmoved by things they want to move it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you don't need to seek out things they want to move it in terms of temptations and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your senses already want to move it all the time.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you're just alone in a cell without any distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, immovability of the mind begins by immovability of behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unbroken virtue, the aggregate of virtue, you have created, the immovable aggregate of certain non-behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: I will not behave towards sensuality, towards, you know, actions of ill-will and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it becomes this solid thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Of certain behavior is not to be done, hasn't been done, you've accomplished that, and that's your aggregate of virtue, as the Buddha referred to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: In the sense that this body is this solid aggregate, well, your virtue becomes this solid aggregate.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't spill over, you don't break through there.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly the beginning of samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sīla, samādhi, pañña.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not sīla over there, then you run and find samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sīla gives the basis for samādhi.
[SPEAKER_01]: On that basis,
[SPEAKER_01]: And that gives the basis for clear seeing, on that basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: Personally, yeah, the aggregates of virtue, you build that up, you create... You build that up, and stop eroding it, stop taking it conditionally, and stop sort of thinking it's kind of a side thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Your practice comes through the framework of your virtue.
[SPEAKER_00]: No other way.